either. Okay, so neck pain.
Your last lecture
in the lower back
covered some general
spine concepts, so
there's no need to
repeat them here.
Mostly I'm going to focus
on cervical specific
issues and make comparisons
with the lumbar.
If you look at most
of the literature,
you'll see that
most of the work
done on the spine
is for the lumbar.
Now, the cervical spine
relative to the lumbar
spine is kind of like
pediatrics relative to internal
medicine. Kids aren't
miniature adults and the
cervical spine isn't the
lumbar spine higher up.
But that's exactly how
it's been treated and
a lot of the work on lumbar
was just extrapolated
onto the c-spine and
assumed to be valid.
For our purposes today,
mostly that's good
enough, but you should be
aware that we do know
less about the cervical
spine with respect to
mechanisms of injury
and disease as well as
effective treatment.
This lecture is about
neck pain, that is axial
pain. Axial meaning
the trunk, head, neck,
anything around the
long axis of the body.
In MRI, when you get these
slices from superior to
inferior, in basic sciences
we call those transverse
planes, but commonly they're
referred to as axial views.
So that's what we're
going to focus on
here, but I have to
talk a little bit about
nerve root and
radicular involvement.
Again contrasting it to
the lumbar spine, here
you have nerve roots exiting
above their respective
vertebrae because of
this eighth cervical
nerve root which I'm sure
you already know about.
So for a central or
paracentral disc protrusion,
the exiting root in the
lumbar is already gone
and you're just getting
the descending nerve
root. In the c-spine
you're catching both and
for a lateral or foraminal
you're getting the
root associated with that
vertebrae as it exits.
When somebody comes to you
with neck pain, even without
pain in the arms, you
still want to do your due
diligence and check them
neurologically. You'll often
see this kind of upper cross
posturing, which is not
specific for anything. This
puts pressure on some of
the discs, some of the
facets, on some of the nerve
root, it overburdens the
muscles. It's just one big
common sign that's low
-hanging fruit for starting to
get in there and correcting
things. But with respect
to the exam, these are the
specific actions and muscles
you test that reflect
strength at those levels
faithfully. Elbow flexion is
for C5, wrist extension is
C6, elbow extension is C7,
finger flexion is C8 but
specifically profundus so
you kind of want to lock
out the proximal interphalangeal
joint and just strength
test flexion at the distal
interphalangeal joint.
And then finger
abduction is C1 but
specifically abductor
digiti minimi.
For sensation, the dermatomes
can overlap, so the
areas I have down here
are dependable every time.
So the dermatomes in
general, the strength
in general, and
definitely the reflexes
are things that you
should just know. So
if you suspect nerve root
involvement because they
have pain and maybe some
numbness in the arm, a very
good confirmation is
spiraling. The original paper
described this as side
bending with a little axial
compression. Now you see
every possible variation, with
and without extension,
with and without rotation,
whichever way you go,
go easy. If it's a
legitimate radiculopathy,
just positioning it like
that usually makes the
symptoms worse. Add
compression if it doesn't,
but do it gingerly.
So I will say that extension
closes off the foramen,
rotating to the ipsilateral
side of symptoms closes
the foramen and side bending
to that side closes the
foramen. So that whenever
you see some variation or
another on an exam, as long
as you know the mechanisms
behind the movements, you
can kind of see through that
particular iteration and
understand what's going on.
And then shoulder abduction can
often make the arm
symptoms better.
This doesn't get much
attention in books or exams,
but basically what's
happening is that you're
taking traction off of the
nerve roots that are coming
down, and laterally, by
abducting the shoulder.
With the lumbar
spine, it was weakness
that was the big
red flag, including
weakness of bowel and
bladder sphincters.
Here you get weakness,
which you can call a
negative finding, but
that's usually accompanied
by this positive finding
of hypertonicity.
Anything lesioning the
upper motor neuron will
interfere with descending
inhibition of the lower
motor neuron, so you get
this excessive firing.
the hand distally,
partly because there's no
interneuron that needs to be
inhibited there. So you'll
often get more typical
weakness, and patients
talk about not having fine
motor control of their
hand, difficulty with
handling buttons or writing.
The reflexes are jumpy.
Babinski can be positive.
Spasticity. Spasticity
is a velocity
-dependent increase in
muscle tone, where the
faster that you move
a joint through its
range of motion, the
more it'll fight you.
Clonus is similar. If
you yank the foot into
dorsiflexion, you get this
tremor of dorsiflexion-plantar
flexion. You can have one
or two beats of clonus,
which suggests a more mild
version of this syndrome,
or you can get a more
sustained version of it.
All of this really speaks
to decreased inhibition by
upper motor neurons. In the
legs, you generally have
extensor tone dominating.
so with their walking it's
hard for them to bend their
knee but distally their
foot drags because it's
weak. This makes for a very
functionally long leg
when you're walking and so
trying to swing your leg
through becomes problematic
because you can't dorsiflex
so you can't lift your
foot off the floor when
your leg is trying to clear.
Likewise you can't bend
your knee and so again it's
harder to clear your leg
as you're swinging through.
These patients
usually end up kind of
throwing their leg out in
this cone formation. We
call it circumduction. It's
not always super obvious,
but once you see it a few
times, you start to get
the consistency in patterns
from one patient to the
next. They can also have
bowel and bladder issues.
So I remember this one
patient that was sent to
me from a primary care
physician for neck pain.
And this patient comes in
with what to me was clearly
a spastic gait, but he
had been like that for a
while and it developed
gradually, so he sort of just
assimilated into it. And
it wasn't terrible, but on
top of that, he had a
sustained clonus, the reflexes
were very brisk, and yeah,
he had spasticity. So
basically, he had a slowly
developing spinal cord injury.
That kind of thing needs
to get a neurosurgical
evaluation. They talk about,
in these circles of like
spine medicine and pain
medicine and spine surgery,
they talk about patients
with cervical stenosis that's
bad enough to give a
presentation like this as
being very vulnerable
because if they fall and they
hit their head and there's
a torque on their neck they
could end up paralyzed.
I've never seen anything
like that in the literature
in terms of cases. I've
covered inpatient spinal
cord injury units for years
and I've never seen a
patient like that but
theoretically it's possible.
So in general you advise
moderation of activity for
these patients and you get
them a spine surgery
evaluation as soon as possible.
The spinal cord is much
thicker in the cervical
region because all those
nerves haven't peeled
off and exited yet
and so even though the
central foramen is bigger
it is a tight fit there.
You can also see how
much bigger the lumbar
vertebral body is compared
to the cervical and you
can see it here as well
and really that just
underscores the function of
the lumbar spine which is
to hold upwards of 65
-70% of your body weight.
One thing to notice over
here is the orientation
of the facet joints.
In the lumbar they're
sagittal so you get mostly
flexion and extension. In
the cervical they're
midway between a coronal
and a transverse plane.
They're about 45 degrees.
The foramen are also
oriented 45 degrees midway
between coronal and sagittal.
In the lumbar they're
90 degrees from the
coronal, which is to say
that they're sagittal,
so the spinal nerve exits
perpendicular to your
screen. In the cervical,
it's coming out about 45
degrees from your screen.
So the foramen and the
transverse processes
are 45 degrees, and
the facet joints.
Imagine that the facet
joints were purely
horizontal or on a
transverse plane. Then
movement there would
give you pure rotation.
Now imagine they were
purely coronal. Movement
there would give you pure
side bending. So when
they tell you that side
bending and rotation are
in the same direction,
like in type 2 somatic
dysfunctions, it's not so
much that they're separate
movements, it's a
hybrid movement. They're
rotating on this oblique
plane, so side bending
and rotation are kind of
baked into each other.
Another thing that sets
cervical vertebrae apart is
the concavity on the top
of the body. The lateral
ends have these processes
that, when you stack
them, make a sort of joint
with the inferior body of
the vertebrae above it.
So these unco-vertebral
articulations act like a
kind of joint and they can
develop hypertrophic changes
with arthropathy just
like facet joints that can
contribute to pathology.
Normal AP view. You can
see the anatomy nicely
here especially the unco
-vertebral articulations.
Normal lateral view.
You can't see the
foramen clearly because
they're 45 degrees
so they're kind of
hiding behind the body.
For comparison,
the transverse process
with the foramen is in
green, the blue are the
articular pillars with the
facet joints that you
palpate all the time in lab.
So if you want to evaluate
the bony intervertebral
foramen on x-ray, you need
to order oblique views.
In the lumbar spine, you
would just get lateral.
The disc is not like it
is in the lumbar spine.
the annulus in the lumbar
spine is like this shell
of spirally oriented
fibers all the way around
360 degrees. It's not
like that in the C-spine.
The fibers are oriented
nearly vertically and it's
really only in the anterior
half around the body. The
back is pretty open except
for the posterior longitudinal
ligament. The pulposus
becomes fibrotic much earlier
in life normally than
the lumbar discs. So disc
herniations aren't the norm
here. That's not to say that
the disc can't protrude and
impinge on the nerve root.
There's no doubt about that.
But as a cause for axial
neck pain, it's less clear
how often that happens.
It almost certainly
does. They've done
assays of the pulposis and
found that it has inflammatory
mediators. They've done
anatomical studies on
the angulus and shown
that it's innervated. And
they've done studies where
they've injected saline into
the discs of normal subject
to high pressures and
mapped out where the pain
was. But all of this amounts
to basic science evidence
and the potential for
pain exists but you can't
make that leap clinically.
Now that disc injection
technique is used diagnostically
but it's technically
challenging to do right.
Probably the best study
we have on this was done
on patients with neck
pain, and it was found that
the disc alone was a cause
in about 16% of patients.
The disc and the facet
joint together, acting
in a coordinated fashion
to create pain, about
40%. But it was a small
sample, and it's hard
to extrapolate that to
the general population.
So the disc can be a source
of pain in the neck, but
how often does that happen
is very unclear. here.
As far as treatment,
ACDF is done for radicular
pain, but they've looked at
how well it takes care of
actual neck pain. The success
rate is not that good.
Most of the literature is
terrible, with basically
anecdotal qualitative descriptions
of how patients felt
better. No pain scales, and
these were done before rigorous
reporting criteria were
in place. But when you look
at the best of the studies,
you see about 20-30%
improvement, which is terrible.
If the disc is
painful and you remove
the disc there shouldn't
be pain anymore.
It was also felt that
movement of a painful
segment induces pain
but that doesn't
fly either hence the
fusion part of it.
Procedures with artificial
disc replacements which
preserve movement actually
do slightly better than
ACDF with regard to neck
pain but not much better.
So across the board it's
hard to know how often
a disc is the problem in
neck pain and on top of
that we have no real
method of treating it. In
my own experience, a
very specific kind of
physical therapy is probably
the best option if you
feel like the disc is
the pain generator there.
These are the areas where
stimulating discs cause
pain, but this map also
relates to facet joints
and where they refer pain
to, which makes sense
because embryologically
they come from the
same somites, so they're
going to share the same
innervation and refer
pain to the same place. So
the facet joints, appropriately
called zygopathyceal
joints, are
definitely involved in
radiculopathy and also
definitely involved in axial
pain. You can prove this by
blocking their innervation,
which is a simple
procedure. Two nerves
innervate each joint and
they're easy to access.
Now, when you look at an MRI
or x-ray, in older patients,
you'll see degenerative
changes. That's not synonymous
with pain or pathology.
So it's a nerve block and
only a nerve block that
can prove if it's a pain
generator. The treatment is then
thermal neurotomy, positioning
a probe over the nerve
and heating it up to
somewhere in the neighborhood
of 70 to 80 degrees Celsius.
After the ablation, the
nerves will grow back, but
it can take upwards of a
year or more, and you can
just keep repeating it.
So it's a good procedure.
The map I showed you for
disc referral patterns
are the same here. If you
look, you'll see that a
C1 to C4 or more around
the head. I don't have a
map of the arms. It's not
well mapped out. There's
some old papers that
have different maps based
on, I think mostly just
clinical experience, but
nobody's really done a
systematic study on this.
Degenerative changes
in a lateral view.
See the interbody space.
On the edge of the vertebral
bodies, you have bone spurs.
See the facets. I mean
honestly the whole picture is a
little overexposed but even
taking that into account
the bony elements just have
more sclerosis and bone
deposition than in the normal.
They're just more opaque.
Here's oblique. This one
is even more pathological.
Look at how small
the foramen are.
The yellow arrow is a
hypertrophied facet joint. The
black arrow is a hypertrophied
uncovertebral joint. All
of that is contributing to
crowding out this foramen.
Any structure in your neck,
particularly the top half,
can contribute to headache
because it can refer
pain to the head via the
trigeminal nucleus caudalis.
That's also how neck pain
can trigger a migraine.
Your foundation of
medicine book tells you
that it can even go as
far down as C6 or C7.
That's technically true
from a pure basic science
perspective, but in
real life it doesn't
happen and there's no
literature evidence to
suggest that it should, so
it's not what you should
be thinking about with
real life patients.
There are your levels
that are most implicated
with C2, C3 being by
far the most common.
Some people do local
blocks of the greater and
lesser occipital nerves
right on the back of
the head. I don't have
a diagram, but you can
find it in any anatomy
atlas or just google it.
Just sticking the needle
right there over the occipital
bone, make sure you're
avoiding the artery and
inject around the nerve
with a mix of lidocaine and
steroid. I've done them,
mostly in fellowship. I
don't like them. The pain
goes away for a while and
the patient goes home with
a numb head, but then they
come back two weeks later
with the same headache.
So I stopped doing them
very quickly. At best, they
might get a couple of months
of relief, but that's very
rare and it's really hard
to select those patients
out. So you end up having to
do them on scores of patients
before you actually get
one or two that actually
get some meaningful relief
from it it doesn't address
the issue it's either facet
joint referring pain there
or if it's a peripheral
nerve greater or lesser being
ensnared in muscle that it
goes through the connective
tissue then either stretching
postural connection
excuse me correction or
manipulation doing that
methodically physical therapy
watching your posture stretching
doing fascial release,
doing that over and over
for months consistently,
that can clear it up. And if
it doesn't, then surgical
release is another option.
So you see where C2, C3 and C3,
C4 goes, but this
is the minimum.
In the studies that
they did, they stopped
injecting when the patient
started to report pain.
But actual pathology
is not as kind as the
researcher. And when pain
continues to intensify,
it also starts to spread.
This map is from recording
the pain distribution
in patients that already
had pain from pathology
and then doing nerve
blocks at the stated levels
and seeing if the pain
disappeared. For example,
on top, when a patient
had pain where it's black,
blocking C1, C2 most
consistently made that pain
disappear compared with
blocking C2, C3, or
C3, C4 for patients that
had pain in that area.
Regardless of the
specific area, relative
to the specific spinal
level, C2, C3 is the
level that's most
common in the overall
population of cervicogenic
headache sufferers.
And then there's muscle.
It's often co-involved
with vertebral issues, but
just muscle alone can
be causative in up to 20
% of chronic neck pain,
and it's a significant
subset of headache as
well. The mechanism that's
responsible for muscle
pain isn't very clear, but
a lot of it has to do with
mechanical insufficiency
from various causes
and baseline weakness.
Muscles will become tight,
sore, they'll be tender,
and they can eventually
develop trigger points.
This is a map of
trigger points of
regional muscles and
the referral patterns.
Clinically I've seen
trigger points mostly in the
upper trapezius and in
the suboccipital muscles.
So any discussion of neck
pain has to consider the
shoulder. If you look back
at that basic map of level
referral almost all of
them skirt around the
shoulder in one area or
another so it's good to make
sure that there is an
actual shoulder pathology in
addition to or instead of
the cervical issue that you
think might be there. So
just basic range of motion,
some special tests for
impingement, labral tears,
ruling out scapular
dyskinesia, which can cause
pain because the muscles
will start to spasm down
around it. All of this
is good. I'm not going to
test you on any of it.
What you're looking here
though is for the pain
reproduction to be very
specific to their chief
complaint and not just some
general vague kind of
sort of hurts like that.
There can be lots of causes
for instability. Most
obvious is severe trauma.
Bony metastases can do it too,
but we're just going to
talk about two general
categories. In OMM, they often
talk about, with regard to
contraindications for
cervical HVLA, Down syndrome
patients, which will have
laxity, but they also have
malformation of the DENS
at times. And I'll put into
this category Ehlers-Danlos
patients, which I see a
lot of because obviously of
the laxity. You can assess
for this very easily on
a lateral x-ray that just
looks at the distance between
the atlas and the dens.
And then in OMM they also talk
about rheumatoid arthritis
and this is instability
because of destruction of
the articulations which create
stability in the cervical
spine. But really it's any of
those spondyloarthropathies,
so your rider syndrome,
psoriatic arthritis,
anything like that, if
they have pain really
high up at the base of
the skull or any sense
of apprehension with
movement, you check it.
With these, I check a
whole C-spine looking for
listesis, and I take
lateral views in neutral,
flexion, and extension.
And I don't care if they
have a little bit of
listesis, but if that
listesis gets worse with
change in position, then
they get introduced to
my spine surgeon friend.
MRI, just for inclusion.
EMG, just for
inclusion. We talked
about this in the
lumbar lecture.
And we talked about
nerve blocks and RFA
already. I would never
do these for arm pain
or leg pain in the lumbar
spine, but I have had
occasions where I did them
for axial pain when the
patient also had limb pain
and it took care of both.
Epidurals are not
for axial pain at
all. It's only for
radicular pain.
In the literature, adverse
effects like spinal cord
injury are not common with
epidurals, but most of them
that are reported are in
the cervical spine. I hated
doing them in fellowship. I
never did them in my practice.
I think a few weeks of pain
relief is not worth the
risk. And at first I
thought I was being overly
conservative, but the
more that I speak to
more senior colleagues
at conferences and people
that I practiced with,
the more I see that that
thinking is not so uncommon.
What
kinds of things can cause
neck pain? I gave you a
similar slide for the lumbar
lecture, but more detailed.
The point is that you just
have to be vigilant always.
Okay one last thing. So
no discussion of neck pain
would be complete without
mentioning whiplash at least.
Usually from a rear impact
collision in a motor vehicle
accident the whole head
and neck whip forward and
then because the distal c
-spine is more mobile and it
has this weight at its end
it starts to rebound first
and then finally the motion
carries through to the
lower c-spine and that extends
too. So there literally
is this whipping motion.
No one really knows if the
pain is from the facet
joints or muscle or disc or
ligaments. It's honestly
probably a combination depending
on each particular
circumstance, but it can range
from mildly to overtly
traumatic with fractures. I've
never seen a fracture on a
whiplash, but they happen.
Overall, however, the
prognosis is very good and
usually within the span
of about three months
with either conservative
measures or sometimes nothing
at all, these patients
usually recover well.
These are my references.
If you have any
questions at all, please
feel free to shoot
me an email and I
hope you enjoyed the
lecture. Thank you.